Okay בוקר טוב Boker tov today's דף daf is הוריות יד, Horayot
yud dalet, הוריות Horayot 14, last דף daf of הוריות, Horayot, smallest
מסכת masekhet in ש"ס. Shas. We pick up on יג עמוד ב
yud gimel amud bet on the first of the wide lines and
we're a little behind but not a problem because it's a very
short דף daf today and we are dealing with the whole issue
about a hierarchy and precedent. הוריות Horayot is not the מסכת masekhet
to do if you are looking for the egalitarian ethos of חז"ל,
Chazal, you know the whole focus of it is of course people
in positions of authority, the בית דין, beit din, the כהן גדול,
kohen gadol, the נשיא, nasi, the king, and then here the last
משניות mishnayot dealt with issues of who takes precedence over whom. Sort
of seems that the hook was that the פר העלם דבר של
ציבור par he'elam davar shel tzibbur comes before the פר par of
the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, but excuse me I got that reversed,
the פר par of the כהן גדול kohen gadol comes before the
פר העלם דבר של ציבור, par he'elam davar shel tzibbur, but that
also led to other ways in which things take precedence, תדיר tadir
more common, you know קדוש מחברו kadosh mechavero holier, and then questions
about status, about you know man, woman, כהן, kohen, לוי, levi, ישראל,
yisrael, also questions of degree of need you know when it comes
to redeeming that a woman you know comes before a man because
of the type of danger that she is in, but also questions
of status and priorities as we discussed yesterday you know Rav Moshe
Feinstein deals with that in terms of issues of like triage. Do
we really take those things למעשה lamaseh practically that that should be
the factor of determining who gets treatment and Rav Moshe sort of
says no no no these is only talking about when all other
relevant factors are equal as in which sort of makes all of
those distinctions moot, but they all of that hierarchy moot, but it
still speaks to a general question about prioritizing you know about like
the about the status within society and who is sort of seen
as holding a higher status.
But then the משנה mishnah introduced the famous last line of the
משנה mishnah introduced you know the idea that תורה Torah is the
big leveler. You know תורה Torah is accessible to all, it's not
a status of birth, and a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham comes before
a כהן גדול עם הארץ, kohen gadol am ha'aretz, so the תורה
Torah ultimately is more important than all of those statuses. Of course
that creates its own hierarchy and not everybody had equal access to
תורה, Torah, but at least it is a certain leveler of status
by birth. So with that we pick up with the first line
here of the first of the wide lines on יג עמוד ב
yud gimel amud bet within the question of תורה Torah status and
different levels within that. So let's take a look. תנו רבנן, Tanu
rabanan, our rabbis taught, כשנשיא נכנס, kshenasi nichnas, when the
נשיא nasi the head of the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, you know the head
the exilarch, this was the position of Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi and his
family,
and also somebody who had a little standing vis-a-vis the Roman government,
the political head of the Jewish people in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael sort of the rabbinic head and the
political head were merged in the role of the נשיא, nasi, you
know in בבל Bavel they were separate
because you know there was the ריש גלותא reish galuta was the
political head, but in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they were merged to
the head of to the role of the נשיא. nasi. So when
the נשיא nasi enters into the בית מדרש beit midrash or to
the or to the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, נכנס כל העם עומדים, nichnas kol
ha'am omdim, everybody stands, ואין יושבים עד שיאמר להם שבו, ve'ein yoshvim
ad sheyomar lahem shvu, and they do not sit until he says
you may be seated. So they he gets explicit permission like when
the judge enters in and the bailiff says all stand and then
he says you may be seated. All right so that's the honor
that they show to the נשיא. nasi. כשאב
בית דין נכנס, Kshe'av beit din nichnas, now when the head of
the בית דין beit din enters, so this is the person that's
in like the secondary role to the נשיא nasi vis-a-vis the סנהדרין
Sanhedrin and the study hall, you know might be that he's more
like the the practical like the executive director you know and the
and the נשיא nasi is sort of like the president, the נשיא
nasi also has more of a public role, an outward-facing role, whereas
the אב בית דין av beit din is the one that like
practically you know is might run more in terms of what happens
in the בית דין beit din in the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So when
the אב בית דין av beit din enters in, but this second
in position second in sort of you know in status here, נכנס
עושים לו שורה אחת מכאן ושורה אחת מכאן עד שישב במקומו, nichnas
osim lo shura achat mikan veshura achat mikan ad sheyeshev bimekumo, so
there's two differences. Number one, it's not that the whole ישיבה yeshiva
or the whole סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, the whole study hall stands, but no
but only like they make a a pathway for him by people
standing on two sides and you know and therefore creates a pathway
that he passes through. So only the people that are directly facing
him as he's walking to the head those are the ones that
stand and also they sit when he sits
but he does not but not that he ex has to explicitly
first give them permission. Okay?
So two ways in which obviously they're showing him honor but a
lesser honor than they're showing the נשיא. nasi. כשחכם נכנס, Kshechacham nichnas,
now the חכם chacham is like the third in
position, it's נשיא, nasi, אב בית דין, av beit din, וחכם. vechacham.
So the חכם chacham might have might be just a title that
just means you know somebody in the... third in authority there,
but maybe this was somebody also that particularly their strength was their
Torah knowledge and maybe it was more of a scholar role than
of an administrative role. Anyway, but when the חכם chacham enters in,
it says so that's even a lower level of authority. אחד עומד
ואחד יושב עד שישב במקומו. echad omed ve'echad yoshev ad sheyeishev bimkomo.
They sort of do the wave as he's passing people. One, you
know, you stand, there's a מצוה mitzvah for also, you know, לפני
שיבה תקום והדרת פני זקן. lifnei seiva takum vehadarta pnei zaken.
So as he's passing people stand and then as he's passing in
front of them and then as he moves beyond them they sit
down. So it's almost like a wave of rising and sitting and
rising and sitting. Not that everybody stands to make a path for
him.
Okay. בני חכמים ותלמידי חכמים. bnei chachamim vetalmidei chachamim. Now sons of
the חכמים chachamim and students of the חכמים. chachamim. You know we
always say somebody is a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham as a way
of like that's the highest appellation of a real Torah scholar. But
technically the word is a, the חכם, chacham, you know, like in
Sefardi communities you still have חכם chacham is the name of the
רב. rav. So the חכם chacham was the sage and the תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim were the students of the sages. And it's really
very obvious here by just saying בני חכמים ותלמידי חכמים. bnei chachamim
vetalmidei chachamim. So their children, you know, and their students. בזמן שרבים
צריכים להם מפסיעין על ראשי העם. bizman sherabbim tzrichim lahem mafsi'in al
rashei ha'am. Okay when the, when the people need them, you know
they can sort of like step over the people. You know so
meaning like if for some reason, you know, they're there in the
crowd that's all in front of, you know, they're there part of
the study hall or the crowd in front of the Sanhedrin. And
if they're needed up front and they're to being called you know
some some reason to call up front there wasn't nice like aisles
to walk through so they could step over people in order to
get to the head. Even though that would be seen as maybe
a little bit, you know, disrespectful to the people they're stepping over.
You know maybe something that sort of shows a little bit though
that that they're like in a higher position than them. But okay
if it was necessary
and so they are they are allowed to do that rather than
having to be I guess even more disruptive to you know to
open up and to make a path.
Now.
יצא לצורך יכנס וישב במקומו. yatza letzorech yikanes veyeishev bimkomo. If somebody
had to go out, you know for a need meaning to go
to the bathroom, then when they come back into the Sanhedrin or
to you know that then or the study hall, you know where
everybody here is gathered, then they can, you know, they don't have
to like stand at the edges. They're allowed to get their way
back to their seat even though it causes a certain degree of
disruption. So this is not here all just about questions of honor
and status. This is more like protocols of how it would work
in the in the, you know, when, you know, in the Sanhedrin
and what do you do to sort of like when do you
make certain allowances and when are there but comes with you know
certain possible disruption.
Okay.
בני תלמידי חכמים שממונים אביהם פרנס על הציבור. bnei talmidei chachamim shemimumim
avihem parnas al hatzibbur. Now the the sons of the students of
the חכמים, chachamim, so that's like two degrees removed from the most
important role of the חכמים. chachamim. Okay if
their parent father, the תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, have a certain role
of you know if they have an appointed role of like of
as leaders of the community. So what type of honor do you
show them? You know, do you show the people that are the
students of these community leaders? Not the students, the children of these
community leaders. בזמן שיש בהם דעת לשמוע נכנסים ויושבים לפני אביהם ואחוריהם
כלפי העם. bizman sheyesh bahem da'at lishmoa nichnasin veyoshvin lifnei avihem ve'achoreihem
klapei ha'am. So if they're able to understand the lectures that are
going on, again it's a little vague are we talking about the
study hall I keep on sort of moving back and forth study
hall or Sanhedrin, you know which is exactly the the setting that
we are talking about. But anyway if they're able to understand the
study that's going on then they can come and sit and be
part of the people and listen to the lecture that's taking place
and they sit right in front of their father. You know because
they're allowed in. It sounds like they themselves are not תלמידי חכמים,
talmidei chachamim, they're not at the normal level that they should be
coming to the שיעור shiur and should be part of that, but
they're the sons and therefore they're given special allowance and they're shown
certain honor and they're allowed to enter in and to sit with
the people even though they're not fully at the right level and
they sit right in front of their fathers, their fathers. ואחוריהם כלפי
העם. ve'achoreihem klapei ha'am.
And their backs are to the people because they're facing front in
order to listen to the lesson. בזמן שאין בהם דעת לשמוע bizman
she'ein bahem da'at lishmoa when they don't have when they And they're
not able to really understand what's going on, so that case נכנסים
ויושבים לפני אבותיהם ופניהם כלפי העם. Nichnasim ve-yoshvim lifnei avoteihem u-fneihem klapei
ha-am.
They sit in front of their fathers so it seems like their
fathers are the ones that are delivering the lecture to the community
and therefore they're sitting like their fathers are facing the community, not
facing their fathers, not with the community facing front but facing with
their fathers facing the community, not because they don't have any role
to play because they're really not there to listen, but they're there
as a way of giving them some honor or giving some latitude
to the father in order to bring his children in. It's sort
of like the rabbi in a שול, shul, sometimes he'll sit in
the front and his kids will sit with him. And
so it's a similar type of an idea. Nobody really thinks that
the kids have any particular role, but they're there because their father
is there and he's the person in this position of authority. Okay.
It's interesting that this is only about בני תלמידי חכמים Bnei talmidei
chachamim and not בני חכמים. Bnei chachamim. The בני חכמים Bnei chachamim
was mentioned in the first case, not here when talking about sitting
with their fathers, it's only the students, only the children of the
תלמידי חכמים. Talmidei chachamim. Anyway, and also limited to cases when their
fathers have a position of authority. I guess if their fathers did
not have a position of authority, then what are their fathers doing
sitting in the front facing the people? They would be sitting among
the people. Okay,
there's obviously a lot about the exact setting here and the exact
institution of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin or the בית מדרש Beit Midrash and
the various roles that we don't fully have fleshed out. All
right.
רבי אליעזר ברבי צדוק אומר אף בבית המשתה עושים אותם סניפין. Rabbi
Eliezer berabbi Tzadok omer af beveit hamishteh osim otam snifin. Even when
this idea that you let the kids sit with their father when
their fathers have a are sitting in a type of a position
of status or honor, that's
not only in the study hall itself, it's even
in even in like when there's even at a wedding party they
would sit with their parents. Again, makes sense. Let's say their parents
are sitting at the dais, dais or whatever, you let the kids
sit with the parent. All right, so סניף snif is like an
add-on, an attachment. It's often used in הלכתי halachic language when you
say סניף להקל, snif le-hakel, an added-on logic that will give you
an extra basis to be lenient. All right, so which means it's
not the thing itself, it's an add-on and attachment. The fundamental person
you're showing honor to here is the parent or the father and
you're letting the kids sit with the father. All right. Now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר מר. Amar Mar. So that's the
ברייתא. Braita. Now we're going to go back and pick it apart
a little bit. יצא לצורך נכנס ויושב במקומו. Yatza litzorech nichnas ve-yoshev
bimkomo.
If somebody had to leave from the סנהדרין Sanhedrin or from the
audience that's gathered there, or again the בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, he
can come back in after he goes to the bathroom, even though
it'll be a little disruptive getting back to his seat. אמר רב
פפא לא אמרו אלא לקטנים אבל לגדולים לא. Amar Rav Papa lo
amru ela le-ktanim aval li-gdolim lo. That's only if he had to
go urinate. But if he had to go number two, if he
had to go defecate, then we do not give him that allowance
to get his way back in. Why? הוי ליה למיבדק נפשיה מעיקרא.
Havei lei lemivdak nafshieh me-ikara. He should have checked himself out originally.
Like if you could go in and all of a sudden you
have to urinate and you didn't have that feeling before and you
didn't know it, there was nothing you could have done. But you
could have checked yourself to see if you were going to have
to go defecate and you should have taken care of that before
you came and you sat down and now because you weren't being
careful you're being disruptive to everybody. Okay. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב
לעולם ילמד אדם עצמו להשכים ולהעריב כדי שלא יתרחק. De-amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav le-olam yilmad adam atzmo lehaskim u-lehaariv kidei shelo yitrachak. A
person should always teach the רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the
name of רב, Rav, a person should always teach himself to get
up early to go to the bathroom, to relieve himself, and also
to do it early in the morning and in the evening, in
order that he does not have to go distant. At the time
when people are around, you'd want to go far away so you
would not be where people could be seeing you. So best to
take care of this like early in the morning and in the
evening when people aren't around
and that way you're planning in advance. So you see that the
idea is this is something that you can take care of and
plan for in advance and you should have done that. All right.
אמר רבא. Amar Rava. So רבא Rava said, רבא אמר האידנא דחלשא
עלמא אפילו לגדולים נמי. Rava amar ha-idna de-chalsha alma afilu li-gdolim nami.
Nowadays we're of a weaker constitution and we can't always just because
we're trying to take care of it in advance does not mean
we can always predict when we're going to need to go, control
when we're going to need to go, and therefore we should have
a little sympathy and latitude even if somebody had to go for
number two
and not blame. and let him come back to his seat. Okay,
fine. רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק אומר אף בית המשתה עושין אותם סניפין.
Rabbi Elazar Beribi Tzadok omer af beis hamishteh osin osam snifin. Now
continuing in the ברייתא, braisa, אף בית המשתה עושין אותם סניפין, af
beis hamishteh osin osam snifin, even at the wedding party, a wedding
celebration, you let the students of the תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, when
their parents have positions of authority, not the students, excuse me, the
children of תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, when their parents have positions of
authority, you let them sit together with their fathers. It's very male
here. When their fathers have a position of authority, you let them
sit with their fathers. So, where are we? אמר רבא בחיי אביהם
בפני אביהם. Amar Rava bechayei avihem bifnei avihem.
But again, that's a status that we only show them when their
father is alive and in the presence of their father, you know,
similar to when it said in the study hall, the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
they sit, you know, with their father where they're facing the people.
So it's not a status that they get on their own. It's
a status that you afford them or recognition you afford them, you
know, as a, exactly the language of סניף, snif, as an add-on
when you are giving that status to their father. Okay.
Now we finally get to a very interesting story to end this
מסכת. masechet. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, said רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, בימי רבן שמעון בן גמליאל נשנית משנה זו. Bimei Rabban Shimon
Ben Gamliel nishnis mishnah zo. At the time of רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל, Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel, this משנה mishnah was taught that gave
different status to the נשיא, nasi, who was רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel, you know, the אב בית דין av beis
din and the חכם. chacham. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל נשיא, Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel nasi, רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel was the נשיא. nasi. רבי
מאיר חכם, Rabbi Meir chacham, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was the חכם.
chacham. רבי נתן אב בית דין. Rabbi Natan av beis
din. כי הוי רבן שמעון בן גמליאל התם, Ki havei Rabban Shimon
Ben Gamliel hasam,
now he's going to tell us the background about why this teaching
came up, that this teaching was issued to give different levels of
recognition for the different people, for the different roles. כי הוי רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל התם, Ki havei Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel hasam, when
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel was there in the
סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, הוי קיימי כולי עלמא מקמיה, havei kaymi kulei alma mikamei,
everybody would rise up. כי הוו עיילי רבי מאיר ורבי נתן, Ki
havu ayili Rabbi Meir veRabbi Natan, and then when רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and רבי נתן Rabbi Natan would come in, הוי קיימי כולי
עלמא מקמייהו, havei kaymi kulei alma mikameihu, everybody would rise up. It
would be the exact same show of honor. אמר רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל, Amar Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
Ben Gamliel said to himself, לא בעו למהוי היכירא בין דילי לדידהו?
Lo ba'u lemehavei hekeira bein dili ledidehu? Isn't it proper that there
should be some distinction between how they're showing honor to me and
honor to them? I mean, I'm in a higher level of authority.
תקין הא מתניתא. Takin ha masnisa.
So he established this משנה, mishnah, this ברייתא, braisa, this ברייתא braisa
that teaches, you know, that everybody stands for the נשיא, nasi, only
the people to make a row for the אב בית דין av
beis din and then like the wave for the חכם. chacham. That
was a ruling that he gave, a תקנה takana he made in
order that, you know, people would understand the different roles that everybody
was playing and the different statuses. Okay. הא מתניתא. Ha masnisa. ההוא
יומא לא הוו רבי מאיר ורבי נתן התם. Hahu yoma lo havu
Rabbi Meir veRabbi Natan hasam. Now interestingly, he issued it when רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי נתן Rabbi Natan weren't there. The way
the גמרא Gemara frames it, it sounds almost like it was by
chance, but one of course wonders, was it totally by chance? Anyway,
he issued this rule of showing different levels of honor when רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי נתן, Rabbi Natan, who were being downgraded
here, were not around. למחר כי אתו, Lemachar ki asu, the next
day when they came to the בית מדרש, beis medrash, חזו דלא
קיימי מקמייהו כדרגילא מילתא. chazu dila kaymi mikameihu kideragila milsa. So
they saw that, hey, people aren't standing up for us, they're continuing
to stand for רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel like
they used to, but for us they're doing a lesser level of
standing than it used to be. Try to figure out what's happening.
עמי מאי האי? Ammei mai hai? What's going on here? How come
people aren't standing like they used to stand for us? אמרו להו
הכי תקין רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Amru lehu hachi takin Rabban Shimon
Ben Gamliel. They said to them, oh, when you weren't here yesterday,
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel established these different ways
of showing honor. אמר ליה רבי מאיר לרבי נתן. Amar lei Rabbi
Meir leRabbi Natan. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי נתן Rabbi
Natan now were obviously pretty upset. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said
to רבי נתן, Rabbi Natan, אנא חכם ואת אב בית דין. Ana
chacham ve'at av beis din. I'm the חכם, chacham, you're the אב
בית דין. av beis din. נתקין מילתא כי לדידן. Naskin milsa ki
ledidan. Let's do something similar for ourselves, you know, or
let's make some plan that will sort of even the scales here
or that will be a proper response to what was just done
to us. מאי נעביד ליה? Mai na'avid lei? What can we do
to him? נימא ליה גלי עוקצין. Nema lei geli uktzin. So let's
plan that tomorrow in the, you know, when we're studying, and this
makes it sound more like it was the בית מדרש beis medrash
than the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. You know, let's say to him, oh, teach
us עוקצין. Uktzin. עוקצין Uktzin is the, you know, it's the last
מסכת masechet in ש"ס. Shas. It's a מסכת masechet in טהרות. Tahoros.
It's very obscure. Who knows עוקצין? Uktzin? Nobody knows עוקצין. Uktzin. Let's
ask him to teach us that. Because again, you know, רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel was the, as I said, the
נשיא, nasi, like the president, you know, the outward facing head,
the titular head, the political head, obviously a major תלמיד חכם, talmid
chacham, but he was not necessarily the same level as the אב
בית דין av beis din and the חכם. chacham. So let's show
him up, let's ask him to teach us one of the most
obscure things in ש"ס. Shas. דלית ליה. Dileis lei. He,
we know that he doesn't have that, meaning he's not a בקי
buki in that, he doesn't know that area. וכיון דלא גמר נימא
ליה, ve'keivan delo gamar nemlei, and when it's clear to everybody that
there's that he doesn't know that material, then we can say מי
ימלל גבורות ה' ישמיע כל תהלתו. mi yemallel gevurot Hashem yashmia kol
tehillato. So, who shall speak the great things of God, will make
known all of God's praises? למי נאה למלל גבורות ה', lemi naeh
lemallel gevurot Hashem, for whom is it appropriate to speak of the
power of God, meaning to sort of represent authority? למי שיכול להשמיע
כל תהלתו, lemi sheyachol lehashmia kol tehillato,
somebody that's able to speak about all of God's greatness, that can
teach all of תורה. Torah. You can't teach all of תורה, Torah,
you don't deserve the status that you have. So basically, it was
a palace coup. They were going to show that he's not a
total master of תורה, Torah, and since of course the role of
the נשיא Nasi was to represent not only the political head but
also it was
a תורה Torah status as well, they will challenge that and demonstrate
to people that he's not deserving of it and
lead to him being kicked out of the
נשיאות, Nasiyut, lead to a popular revolt. ונעבריה, venavrei, and then that'll
allow us to remove him from the post. ואהוי אנא אב בית
דין ואת נשיא, va'ahavei ana av beis din ve'at nasi, and we'll
all go up a level, I'll become the אב בית דין av
beis din and you רבי נתן, Rabbi Nason, you'll become the נשיא.
Nasi. So okay, that was the plan. שמעיה רבי יעקב בן קרשי,
shameia Rabbi Yaakov ben Korshai, so this personage that we've never heard
of before, רבי יעקב בן קרשי Rabbi Yaakov ben Korshai overheard them.
אמר, amar, דילמא חס ושלום אתי מילתא לידי כיסופא, dilma chas veshalom
asi milsa lidei kissufa,
God forbid this will lead to a shaming, an embarrassment of רבן
גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. I mean, you think? They're going to try to
depose him by showing that he's not the biggest תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham and that he doesn't have all, you know, he's not a
total master. Of course it's going to lead to embarrassment. Meaning, but
he was concerned about that, about the public shaming of the נשיא
Nasi and what they were going to do to him. אזל יתיב
אחורי עליתיה דרבן גמליאל. azal yasiv achorei aliyasa de'Rabban Gamliel. So he
went and he sat himself down, you know, on the other side
of like the second story, you know, the study of רבן גמליאל.
Rabban Gamliel. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel in his home, he was there
on the second level of the house and whatever it was, and
he was sitting outside the house, right under the window, and פשט
גרס
ותנא גרס ותנא. pashat geres vetana geres vetana. He basically, he went
ahead and he explained, you know, the he learned out loud everything
from עוקצין. Uktzin. He explained it, he taught it, he repeated it,
he taught it, he repeated it, you know, and went over and
over and over again, talking about saying the משניות mishnayot of עוקצין
Uktzin and explaining them.
Okay, so מאי דקא מתא? mai de'kamasa? So רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
said, what's going on here? Why is this rabbi sitting outside learning
this? דילמא חס ושלום איכא במדרשא מידי, dilma chas veshalom ika bemidrasha
midi, maybe there's something going on in the בית מדרש. beis medrash.
Like he's obviously sending me a signal. He's trying to tell me,
hey, you better study עוקצין, Uktzin, something's happening. And obviously רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel might have a reason to suspect something is happening because
he made sure to impose this different level of demonstrating honor, you
know, when רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי נתן Rabbi Nason weren't
there. Okay, but he didn't know exactly what it was, but he
said, he's telling me, buddy, you better study עוקצין. Uktzin. Okay, so
דילמא חס ושלום איכא במדרשא
מידי, dilma chas veshalom ika bemidrasha midi,
something's going on in the בית מדרש. beis medrash. יהב דעתיה וגרסה.
yaiv daitei vegerasha. So he put his mind to it and he
studied this, these משניות mishnayot of עוקצין. Uktzin.
And למחר אמרו ליה, lemachar amru lei, ניתי מר וניתני בעוקצין. neisei
mar venisnei be'Uktzin. So then the next day came and he showed
up in the בית מדרש beis medrash and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and רבי נתן Rabbi Nason said, the master, let the master teach
us עוקצין, Uktzin, we're interested in learning some of מסכת עוקצין. Masechet
Uktzin. פתח ואמר. patach ve'amar.
Oh, he said, great, let me tell you. And there it was,
he knew the משניות, mishnayot, he knew how to explain them, he
knew you know how to open the discussion about them. This was
something that was so obscure they were assuming he didn't know, maybe
wouldn't even be able to know the text itself, and he was
able to now teach the text and explicate it.
So בתר דאוקים, batar de'ukim, so then, you know, after he had
completed, אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to them, אילו לא גמירנא,
ilu lo gamirna, if I had not studied this last night and
known it, כספיתון, kisfitun, you would have embarrassed me, you would have
shamed me. I know what you were planning on doing and I
sort of preempted it.
Okay, פקיד ואפקינהו מבי מדרשא. pakid ve'afkinu mibei midrasha. He gave the
order and they were kicked out of the בית מדרש. beis medrash.
So they were, and here by the way, you know, this is
by the way the ארמית Aramaic part, this is all in ארמית,
Aramaic, this is so this is a later text. The earlier text
that spoke about the ordering, you know, without mentioning any of these
figures, just אב בית דין, av beis din, נשיא, Nasi, etc., did
not say if the setting was the סנהדרין Sanhedrin or the בית
מדרש. beis medrash. Here certainly in the בבלי, Bavli, it's telling you
know we're in a very בית מדרש beis medrash setting. Okay, anyway,
so they got kicked out of the בית מדרש. beis medrash.
הוו כתבי קושיאתא בפתקא ושדו התם. havei katvei kushyasa be'pitka veshadu hatam.
So they were still allowed to participate in the learning, I mean
these were the biggest תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, okay, but they weren't
allowed to be in the room. So they listened. through the crack
in the door, whatever they did, in the window, and if they
had a question about what was being studied in the study hall,
they would write on a little piece of paper and they would
send it in
and it would get
read. דהוה מפרק מפרק, De-hava mifrak mifrak, the things that were able
to be answered by Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and all the חכמים
Chachamim that were there in the study hall, they would answer. דלא
הוה מפרק, De-la hava mifrak, if they couldn't come up with an
answer, כתבו פירוקא ושדו, Kasvei peruka veshadu, they, you know, Rabbi Natan
and Rabbi Meir themselves would write the answer and send it in.
So meaning when they were writing the question, it wasn't so much
that they didn't know the answer and they needed an answer. They
were sort of saying, "Hey, what you're teaching over there, there's some
problems with it. Let me show, let me challenge you in terms
of what's being taught." And then when they weren't able to come
up with an answer, they would say, "Well, here's the way you
could answer it."
So it was very clear, you know, that the biggest תלמידי חכמים
Talmidei Chachamim were on the outside. They were the ones that were
able to challenge, they were the ones that were able to know
how to answer the challenges. Okay,
so אמר להו רבי יוסי, Amar lehu Rabbi Yosei, so Rabbi Yosei
said to them, meaning to the, you know, to all of the
חכמים Chachamim that were gathered,
תורה מבחוץ ואנו מבפנים. Torah mi-bachutz ve-anu mi-bifnim. The real תורה Torah
is outside of the study hall, it's Rabbi Natan and Rabbi Meir,
they're the ones that represent the highest level of the תורה. Torah.
What are we doing inside the study hall? Either we should go
out to them or they should come in to us. So
אמר להן רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Amar lahen Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
ניילינהו. Naylinehu. So Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel said, "Okay, fine. Let's bring
them back in. I punished them, I'll accept that they can enter
back in because we need them, obviously, you know, we care ultimately
about תורה Torah and they're the biggest תלמידי חכמים." Talmidei Chachamim.
ניילינהו, Naylinehu,
hold on, מיהו נקנסינהו. Mihu niknasinehu. But we're going to fine them,
we're going to punish them. They'll be part of the discussions, but
they're going to have to really live with the consequences of their
actions.
דלא נימרו שמעתא משמייהו. De-la nemru shamata mi-shmaiyehu. We're not going to,
even you know, we want their תורה, Torah, but we're not going
to attribute it to them. They no longer deserve the honor of
having their תורה Torah of being remembered, you know, as the ones
who have, you know,
as the ones who gave the תורה Torah that they taught. Okay,
we're not going to mention their names.
דלא נימרו שמעתא משמייהו. De-la nemru shamata mi-shmaiyehu. אסיקו לרבי מאיר אחרים
ולרבי נתן יש אומרים. Asiku le-Rabbi Meir Acherim u-le-Rabbi Nasan Yesh Omrim.
So, you know, when you say אחרים אומרים Acherim omrim in a
ברייתא Braisa or in a משנה, Mishna, we know that that means
Rabbi Meir. Well, this is the story of how that happened. So
we're going to still perpetuate their teachings, but we're not going to
associate their names with it. From this point on, you know, that's
funny, a lot of משניות Mishnayos say רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir
omer, but you know, and explicitly say Rabbi Meir's positions, but maybe
this means from this point on, if there's a teaching of theirs
that we want to include in the משנה, Mishna, in the ברייתא,
Braisa, you know, passing it down in the oral tradition, we're not
going to associate their names with it. We're going to say "others
say," and for Rabbi Natan, יש אומרים, Yesh Omrim, "there's those who
say."
אחוו להו בחלמייהו. Achvu lehu be-chalmaiyehu.
Okay, so that was the decision. So now it's not clear, by
the way, if they still were חכם Chacham and אב בית דין.
Av Beis Din. It sounds like yes, it sounds like this was
the only lasting relevance of their, you know, the lasting part of
their punishment was that from at least this point on, their teachings
would not be recorded in their names. So it was shown to
them, to Rabbi Meir and to Rabbi Natan, in a dream, זילו
פייסו ליה לרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Zilu payesu leh le-Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel. "Go and appease him." It's interesting that it had to be
shown to them, you would think that they don't want to be
in a state, in this standing, you know, of displeasure from the
נשיא Nasi and also living with the consequences of not having their
teachings recorded in their names. But anyways, they were,
it was seen in their dreams, a heavenly message that they should
go and try to make up with Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. רבי
נתן אזל, Rabbi Nasan azal, Rabbi Natan went and tried to make
up with him. רבי מאיר לא אזל, Rabbi Meir lo azal, Rabbi
Meir didn't
go. אמר דברי חלומות לא מעלין ולא מורידין. Amar divrei chalomos lo
maalin ve-lo moridin. He said, "Dreams don't mean anything. Yeah, don't have
to listen to the dream, it's nonsense, I don't believe in dreams."
כי אזל רבי נתן, Ki azal Rabbi Nasan, he's going to live
with the consequences of that. When Rabbi Natan went, אמר ליה רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, Amar leh Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel said, נהי דאהני לך קמרא דאבוך למהוי אב בית
דין שווינך נמי נשיא. Nehi de-ahani lach kamara de-avuch le-me-havi Av Beis
Din shavinach nami Nasi. So you know, if you're coming now to
apologize, you're giving me an opportunity to tell you how I actually
feel about what just happened. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel said to him,
"It might be that the קמרא, kamara, which actually says is like
the golden belt,
the status of your father might have been enough to that you
could become the אב בית דין. Av Beis Din. Did you also
want to be the נשיא? Nasi? Like hey, you were a little
too big for your britches." Actually very appropriate for the קמרא, kamara,
for the belt. It's interesting that he mentions your father because you
know, the אב בית דין Av Beis Din and the חכם Chacham
were really, this gets back to the whole משנה Mishna about the
hierarchy of תורה Torah learning. The נשיא Nasi was the inherited post.
We've been talking about inherited posts as well כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
which is if that the son of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
would be the first one that they would look at if he
was fit to be the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol he would get
it, otherwise you go somewhere else. The king would always be that
was a hereditary position and the נשיאות, Nesiyut, you know, the נשיא
Nasi was the family of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and רבי Rebbi
and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and so on. So it's interesting that
he's claiming that רבי נתן's Rebbi Nason position is based on the
honor and the status of his father, since רבי נתן's Rebbi Nason
position is really a תורה Torah position and based on his knowledge
of תורה. Torah. But anyway, he basically says,
you know,
you did not deserve, how could you have thought that it was
appropriate for you to be the נשיא? Nasi?
And that was pretty arrogant. So
מסני ליה רבי לרבי שמעון בריה. masni lei Rebbi le-Rebbi Shimon brei.
So now רבי, Rebbi, next generation, was teaching רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
his son
אחרים אומרים אילו היה תמורה, Acherim omrim ilu haya temurah, top of
יא עמוד א, Yud Aleph amud Aleph, לא היה קרב. lo haya
kareiv. So teaching a teaching of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and again
teaching it in the name of אחרים, Acherim, others say if it
was a תמורה Temurah it would not have been offered. So this
has to do with the whole issue
about מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah that if
you have your new sheep that were born that year walk through
a gate and you count one, two, three, four, and every tenth
one has the status of מעשר בהמה. Maaser Behemah. But if you
make a mistake and you count number nine, ten, and you count
the number ten, ten, or you count the number eleven, ten, all
of those would have also the status of a קרבן Korban status
and that they would be offered, although slightly different. Anyway, the question
was, do you treat the number eleven that was called ten, do
you treat that as something that was inherently קדוש Kadosh or is
it a type of a תמורה, Temurah, something that was an attempt
that was exchanged for another thing? Since you had already called ten
number ten and now you're calling eleven number ten, do we sort
of see it like it's קדוש Kadosh because you tried to exchange
it for another ten? Does it have a תמורה Temurah status or
is it directly קדוש? Kadosh? And the הלכה Halacha with it is
that you bring it as a שלמים. Shelamim. So אחרים, Acherim, רבי
מאיר, Rebbi Meir, said if it were a תמורה Temurah it would
not have been offered up as a שלמים, Shelamim, you know, so
therefore that proves that you do not, because the הלכה Halacha is
that when it comes to בכור Bechor and מעשר, Maaser, you know,
you only bring them and you do not bring their תמורה. Temurah.
So since the הלכה Halacha is that number eleven is קדוש Kadosh
and it is offered up as a קרבן, Korban, okay, and he
says and if it were תמורה Temurah of מעשר Maaser the הלכה
Halacha is תמורה Temurah of מעשר Maaser is not offered up, that
shows that the קדושה Kedushah of number eleven is not the קדושה
Kedushah of תמורה, Temurah, it is an inherent קדושה. Kedushah. Okay,
so anyway, that was it, but it was some teaching about about,
you know, of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir that was in the name
of אחרים, Acherim, others. So אמר ליה מי הם אלו שמימיהם אנו
שותים ושמותם אין אנו מזכירים. amar lei mi heim ellu she-mymeha anu
shotim u-shmotam ein anu mazkirin. So רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon said, very
nice little ditty here, who are these people that we're drinking from
their waters? You know, that was such a like, not only is
it רבי מאיר's Rebbi Meir ruling, but it showed the depth of
the understanding of how he demonstrated that it wasn't a תמורה. Temurah.
Who are these, we're drinking from their waters, but we're not mentioning
who their names are. Others say, who are these others?
So אמר ליה בני אדם שביקשו לעקור כבודך וכבוד בית אביך. amar
lei bnei adam she-bikshu l'akor kvodcha u-kvod beis avicha. These are the
people that tried to uproot your honor and the honor of your
father's house. They were trying to foment
a rebellion and a palace coup and that would have taken our
entire family, would have taken away the נשיאות Nesiyut from our entire
family. There, by the way, is בית אביך, beis avicha, right, because
the נשיאות Nesiyut is an inherited post. By the way, one also
wonders if in this telling the reason they picked something about תמורה,
Temurah, about exchanging the thing for the thing itself and does it
get קדושה, Kedushah, you know, there's a certain way in which that
relates to the whole story about trying to depose רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel and take his place and who is the real one and
who is the one that's called that name. Okay, so anyway, so
רבי Rebbi said these are people that are, were our, like could
have completely
destroyed our status, so we're not saying their names. By the way,
it seems that even though רבי נתן Rebbi Nason made up with
רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, it didn't change the idea
that this apathy remained in its place.
Okay, so
אמר ליה, amar lei, so שמעון, Shimon, רבי's Rebbi son, said to
רבי, Rebbi, גם אהבתם גם שנאתם גם קנאתם כבר אבדה. gam ahavatam
gam sinatam gam kinatam kvar avda. He says, come on, that's old
history, you know, their love, their hatred, their jealousy, it's all lost,
it's all past history. Do we have to sustain this holding on
to these fights? Let's move beyond it.
אמר ליה... amar lei... The enemy, says the swords cease, you know,
הא חזית, ha chazit, האויב תמו, haoyev tamu, even after the enemy
has ceased, חרבות לנצח, charavot lanetzach, the swords still remain, you know.
So yes, he says
that the damage that they did still, or maybe it means that
had they succeeded the damage would still remain or that the threat
is still there. We have to do certain things to make it
clear, you know, to protect our status and to show the consequences
of challenging the status. So yes, even though they're dead and gone,
it's still, you know, it's not appropriate to mention their names.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, הני מילי היכא דאהנו מעשיהם, hani mili heicha
de'ahanu ma'aseihem, he said fine, that idea that the swords, the damage
still remains and you know, and that remains, that's if their actions
had succeeded. רבנן לא אהנו מעשיהם, Rabanan lo ahanu ma'aseihem, but it
didn't succeed. So if it didn't succeed and it was just an
attempted coup, why is it so important to hold on to it?
הדר איסני ליה, Hadar isni lei, אמרו משום רבי מאיר, amru mishum
Rebbe Meir, אילו היה תמול לא היה קרב. ilu haya temol lo
haya karev. So Rebbe softened a little bit and he didn't still
keep on calling Rebbe Meir אחרים, acherim, but he didn't say Rebbe
Meir said, he said it was said in the name of Rebbe
Meir, so to still distance him a little and not give Rebbe
Meir the full כבוד kavod even of his own teachings.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, אפילו רבי דענוותנא הוא, afilu Rebbe deanvetana hu,
even Rebbe that's very humble, תנא אמרו משום רבי מאיר, tana amru
mishum Rebbe Meir, אמר רבי מאיר לא אמר. amar Rebbe Meir lo
amar. He said they said in the name of Rebbe Meir, he
didn't say Rebbe Meir said. Sometimes even if you personally are humble,
felt it's important to do certain things to protect the status, you
know, the status, it's not just about you personal, it's about the
role, the position, the office, and that was necessary to protect the
status so you do not challenge the נשיאות. nesiyut. Okay. אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rebbe Yochanan, פליגי בה רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל ורבנן, pligi ba Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel verabanan, so that
is the end of that story. So that's all very interesting about,
you know, hierarchy, נשיא אב בית דין חכם, nasi av beit din
chacham, like a Torah hierarchy, but is it all based on merit?
The נשיא nasi role is really based on an inherited post and
how that was sort of challenged and put down. So we're going
to end again with another two sort of stories also about hierarchy
within Torah roles. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rebbe Yochanan, פליגי בה רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל ורבנן, pligi ba Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel verabanan, the
debate of Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and the Rabbanan. So Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel once again, חד אמר סיני עדיף וחד אמר עוקר הרים
עדיף. chad amar Sinai adif vechad amar oker harim adif. One said
Sinai, like הר סיני, Har Sinai, like getting the Torah as straight
from, you know, straight from God, meaning so what this really means
is like the knowledge of the content is more important, and the
other said uprooting the mountain, like uprooting the mountain is more important,
meaning analysis. What's more important, like the knowledge of the facts and
of the texts or the strength of analysis, and which one deserves
to be at a higher status, you know, in terms of like
if for a Torah role. Now, so first of all it's interesting,
right? סיני ועוקר הרים, Sinai ve'oker harim, the mountain, getting it from
the top of the mountain, but being to uproot the mountain, meaning
to be able to challenge and break it down and you know,
and analyze it in order to understand it more deeply. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says.
רב יוסף סיני
ורבה עוקר הרים. Rav Yosef Sinai verabba oker harim. Now Rav Yosef
knew, you know, he was the one that was the repository of
all the knowledge.
Rabbah was the one that had the strength of analysis. שלחו להתם,
Shelachu lehatam,
so they sent, you know, to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, איזה מהם
קודם, eizeh meihem kodem, which one should have is, has a higher
status and should be given like an honor of office.
שלחו להו סיני עדיף, Shelachu lehu Sinai adif, they sent Sinai is
better, why?
דאמר מר הכל צריכין למרי חטייא, de'amar mar hakol tzerichin lemarei chitaya,
because it's
said everybody needs the master of wheat. So what does this mean?
This is a different metaphor, not the getting it from the mountain
or uprooting the mountain, but the idea of learning as a type
of, you know, harvesting, you know, and the knowledge
is the kernels of wheat, חטין. chittin. Okay. And what is the
analysis? So it's interesting here, like the word
for to learn, we had it before, is גרס. garas. גרס Garas
like גרש כרמל, geresh karmel, לגרוס, ligros, which means to chew, to
grind. So you take the wheat, that's the knowledge, and you know,
that's the repository, that's like the texts, the received knowledge, and then
in order to analyze it, what do you do? Wheat by itself
you can't, you can't eat wheat, you know, you gotta grind it
and turn it into flour and turn it into bread. So a
גרסא girsa and לגרוס ligros all come from the same word of
like the grinding of the wheat. Okay, but he said, no, you
know, the סיני Sinai is more important because everybody needs the wheat.
You can't get started without the wheat. You can't do analysis if
you don't have the knowledge and the texts in order to analyze
them. Now this again remember was an oral tradition. Nobody had a
bookshelf full of all of the משניות Mishnayot and all of the
ברייתות Braitot and all of the the teachings until that point. So
you needed somebody who really knew all of the teachings before you
could then start with the analysis. Now that's certainly true, like you
know, if you have to choose one or the other, who's the
person we're going to bring to our town, you know, to be
the רבי Rebbi or who's going to teach our kids or whatever,
you can't have somebody who just has a good analytical mind if
you don't, you know, you gotta start with the material. But that's
not exactly necessarily the right answer to like who deserves the greatest
honor if you have both of them in the town and you're
able to bring the two of them together. But that was the
answer since everybody needs the one who knows the material, that one
deserves the greater honor. Okay, ואפילו הכי v'afillu hachi and even though
that was the response they received, לא קיבל רב יוסף עליה, lo
kibel Rav Yosef alei, Rav Yosef refused to accept the office. So
therefore מלך רבה, malach Rabbah, so Rabbah was given the office of
the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva apparently or something similar, עשרים ושתים שנין,
esrim v'shartai shnin, twenty-two years. והדר מלך רב יוסף v'hadar malach Rav
Yosef and only then, you know, did Rav Yosef take over the
office. וכל שני דמלך רבה v'chol shnei d'malach Rabbah and as long
as Rabbah was the head of the בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, רב
יוסף אפילו אומנא לביתיה לא קרא, Rav Yosef afillu umna l'beiteh lo
kara, he would show total deference. This is in contrast to the
whole רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, רבי Rebbi and whatever story, רבן גמליאל,
Rabban Gamliel, excuse me, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי נתן. Rabbi
Natan. Here, you know,
Rav Yosef himself deserved the office, stepped back, allowed Rabbah to take
the office, and did not want to show, showed total deference to
Rabbah so he would not even call a bloodletter, a doctor to
his house. He wouldn't ask the doctor to make house calls, you
know? Doctor would make house calls to important people, but he said,
"No, I'm going to go to the doctor's office for the appointment.
Rabbah's the important person around here, not me."
Okay, אביי ורבא ורבי זירא ורבה בר מתנא הוו יתבי, Abaye v'Rava
v'Rabbi Zeira v'Rabbah bar Matna hava yasvi, one last story. Abaye and
Rava and Rabbi Zeira and Rabbah bar Matna were sitting together וצריכי
רישא v'tzrichi reisha and they needed somebody to sort of be the
head of the group. It's not exactly clear why they needed somebody
to be the head, you know the תוספות הראש Tosafot haRosh sort
of explains that they needed somebody who was like you know the
way they would learn is somebody would teach the material and then
it would get challenged and discussed or whatever and you know and
then they would move on to the next material. So you needed
somebody to, it wasn't just everybody learning in חברותא, chavruta, you know
the whole structure was you needed somebody to sit at the head.
Okay, אמרי amri so who is going to sit at the head?
So they said כל דאמר מילתא ולא מפרך ליהוי רישא, kol d'amar
milta v'lo mifrach lehvei reisha, anybody who can teach something and we
won't be able to, as they say in the ישיבה Yeshiva world,
שלוג schlug it up and we won't be able to disprove it,
that person, you know, will be the one that will sit at
the head. דכולהו איפרך, d'kulehu ifrach, everybody said something that was able
to be challenged. דאביי לא איפרך d'Abaye lo ifrach and Abaye's was
not able to be challenged. So חזייה רבה לאביי, chazyei Rabbah l'Abaye,
so Rabbah according to this גירסא, girsa, some have it as רבא
Rava because Rava was the one who was right there, saw Abaye
דגבה רישיה d'geba reisha that he was you know,
this could be read like he was showing arrogance, he was lifting
up his head, but the way רש״י Rashi reads it is that
you know that he showed that it was a successful time for
Abaye, that Abaye was on the rise. אמר ליה amar leh so
he said to him נחמני פתח ואימא, Nachmani petach v'eima, Nachmani open
up and teach. So meaning like he you know he was enthusiastic,
he was encouraging rather than being, it seems like this is a
little again a response to the first story, rather than being resentful
he was happy for Abaye. Open up and teach.
Abaye's actual name, given name, is נחמני. Nachmani. Some say that his
you know
his uncle was רבה בר נחמן Rabbah bar Nachman so that's why
he was called נחמני. Nachmani. And Abaye actually was an orphan and
some say אביי Abaye is an acronym for אשר בך ירוחם יתום.
asher becha yerucham yatom. In you God, you know the orphan will
be consoled. Another explanation for the name of אביי Abaye is that
since he was a student of רבה Rabbah and Rabbah's father was
רבה בר נחמן Rabbah bar Nachman and Abaye's name was נחמני, Nachmani,
sort of like the name of his father with an extra י,
yud, you know? And he didn't want to call him נחמני Nachmani
because that would be like you know calling him by his father's
name,
you know, and referring to his using his father's name in conversation
you know to a student who he's treating as his you know
as somebody
who he's in a superior position towards. So instead he called him
אביי, Abaye, sort of like a change of אבא Abba which is
pretty interesting. Anyway, the ראש Rosh says that. All right, anyway, last
line: איבעיא להו, iba'u lehu, they asked the question, רבי זירא ורבה
בר רב מתנא הי מינייהו עדיף? Rabbi Zeira v'Rabbah bar Rav Matna
hei minaihu adif? If it was between Rabbi Zeira and Rabbah bar
Matna, which one would be better? Again, better... Better in what sense?
Better to have in the בית מדרש, Beis medrash, better to have
as a teacher, as a חברותא, chavrusa, deserving of more honor seems
to be the context here, but anyway, what was that question about?
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira חריף ומקשי, charif u'makshe, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
was very,
very sharp, you know, he had a quick intelligence, quick thinking, he
asked a lot of questions, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira is always the
one in the גמרא Gemara that's asking questions and like making these
hair-splitting, you know, issues. So, but רב מתנה, Rav Masna, רבה בר
רב מתנה Rabba bar Rav Masna מתון ומסיק. masun u'masik. רבה בר
רב מתנה, Rabba bar Rav Masna, he's not so fast, he's not
so sharp, he takes his time, he thinks things through, but as
a result, he comes up with a good conclusion, it's not just
really strong questions, you know, he's slower, slow thinking and comes up
with a, is able to come up with like the bottom-line הלכה.
halakha. So which one is better? מאי? Mai? So the גמרא Gemara
ends appropriately with תיקו. teiku. Okay, so very interesting way of ending
the מסכת masechet about questions about authority and תורה Torah authority and
then questions about about like the different ways and strengths and necessary
roles that people can play within the learning of תורה. Torah. הדרן
עלך מסכת הוריות וסליקא לך מסכת הוריות. Hadran alach Masechet Horayot ve'silka
lach Masechet Horayot. מזל טוב Mazel tov finishing this מסכת masechet and
tomorrow we start זבחים. Zevachim.